all right here we go uh so uh welcome
especially people here at Diamond
Mountain nice to see you good morning
some people haven't seen for a long time
nice to see you and everybody online
thank you for being
here and I had a I couldn't sleep last
night uh because something was bothering
me and uh some new idea of course and uh
I was thinking about uh the medicine
Buddha mantras and
uh I was thinking about what was
the what was the most amazing mantras I
ever saw in my life and I thought you'd
like to
know uh because I saw many high teachers
do mantras and you know many many high
teachers doing mantras and doing
surprising things
so it was
and my teachers baseball
team the New York
Mets had by the way you guys are too
young but they were the worst team in
history uh they I think they lost they
have a record still I think it's 17
games in a row they lost and they had
the lowest record in history and uh my
teacher decided to support them and uh
he was doing mantras the whole
season and they start
winning and then they're winning more
and
more and then finally they reached
the ALCS did the World Series
preliminary and uh so one of his
favorite
batter came up to bat his name is d
strawberry okay and
uh I don't know my teach's going like
this and I'm like R that's cheating you
know and he's like I don't care
you he's like this you know and then he
says what's the farthest wall in the
whole
stadium uh you know what would be the
best hit in in the whole stadium and I
said right field at sha Stadium right
field fence is built higher it's like
much higher it's like 30 feet higher so
it's impossible to hit a ball over the
right field sent he's like right field
fence and he's he's counting his
M then the pitch
[Music]
came yeah that's the pitcher very famous
no one can hit his balls you
know and
then he hit the ball and then okay if if
you look up at the ACI logo and you go
to the right you can see the
ball okay and you can see they built the
wall higher on the right side you see
that's extra wall and nobody can hit
over that you know it's impossible and
the ball wasn't far enough to go over
the wall and he's like
and
then the ball is over the green
sign and it just like
goes and it went over the and it hit a
home run and they won the World
Series and impossible totally impossible
so that's the best mons I ever
saw and most important ones also
so I we're going to talk
about uh this medicine Buddha practice I
think
um I don't like Superstition personally
I don't like Buddhism become
Superstition it it's a very irritating
to me and uh I I don't like it you know
when people light incense and say I hope
my enemy breaks his arm tomorrow you
know I don't like this kind of stuff and
I I don't believe in it and uh so
I but but it's true we are going to do
medicine Buddha mantras and we are going
to try to help
people cure people from
sickness and uh for me it's it's
difficult for me I I don't feel
comfortable with it you know I can
understand doing mantras
to stop the suffering of the whole world
or to stop your death or something like
that but to say I hope hope my uncle's
cold gets better tomorrow or something
like that and then to be disappointed
when the MRA doesn't work for you I
think uh I don't know the whole thing
feels like Superstition to me and I I
never liked it and I I frankly I was
never much attracted to medicine for
practice and uh and so my friends asked
me would I teach it and I do have a
initiation from a very very high
Loma uh when I was quite young and uh so
I had that teaching and I was granted
that
teaching uh and I believe in the
medicine for the practice but I think
you need to understand it to for it to
work I I think if you do it as a
Superstition it it won't work or or
it'll just be something
superstitious and and it just like you
know in America if you have a rabbit's
foot you get good luck or something like
that the poor Rabbit doesn't get good
luck uh but uh you know can the medicine
Buddha practice work and I say yes uh
but for it to work uh you have to
understand emptiness you have to study
emptiness so it's kind of like a
marriage between medicine Buddha and and
Perfection of wisdom you you you can't
practice medicine Buddha it won't work
for you if you don't understand the
Perfection of
emptiness uh and and then if you try to
do emptiness but you don't care that
people are sick that's also strange so I
think they go together very
sweetly and it's a very nice uh
combination and I'm happy that people
asked me to teach it and um so the the
idea I have is uh to we're gonna
continue hi Jenny thank you for
everything uh the idea is that uh I
asked Tim how
many uh medicine Buddha classes should I
do and how many Naga classes should I do
I in
Naga uh because uh we've been
reading uh the greatest book ever
written on emptiness which is neous
wisdom and uh and I said well how many
classes each and he said well I thinking
six wisdom classes and four medicine
buding classes so I started to prepare
and then uh then suddenly I saw where
where uh do you know that genetic Helix
thing you know and I I suddenly I saw
this thing where they uh you could teach
them together you could braid them
together and it would be very beautiful
uh so I I feel there's a way that you
could uh teach them
intertwin and uh so that's what we're
going to do so instead of half and half
we'll just uh intertwine them and uh
we'll get a good dose of emptiness tees
and a good dose of medicine Buddha
teachings and um I think it's it came
out very beautiful I'm very excited
about it I threw out uh the first
classes I had prepared and
I you know replaced them which is how
you drive Tim and Al
crazy and it seems to have
worked uh
so I changed all the classes a couple
days ago and uh we're going to go
through wisdom and medicine Buddha
together uh like a braiding your hair or
something if you have hair uh okay so
we're gonna go through that and
uh we've done some wisdom already we
started I think four sessions
ago uh I'm using a
commentary by CH
lad uh who I think is one of the
greatest commentary writers in history
he he used to have dreams about flying
to the west and teaching emptiness in
the west that was 400 years ago and you
know he didn't know about America or
anything but he he used to have a lot of
dreams about it and he's a great
great writer has a western style he has
a kind of style that that is easy for us
to understand uh so he wrote an
explanation of wisdom wisdom is a
actually a long
poem and uh it's got
27 sections to the poem 27 different
topics and uh and it's I think it's some
of the greatest poetry ever written uh
but we've been using it uh recently we
are filming uh a thing called peacock
parenting project and that's uh sagei uh
Aral and his wife nor
ibraim and uh we were flirting with
roomy's
poetry and some other poetry for two
years we taught it we had a big program
in the Russian language and then
uh suddenly we had this idea to focus on
how to be a good parent
and I thought that was good for me to
teach because I don't know anything
about it
and so uh now somebody said you've had
thousands of kids so is probably true
but uh so this last month we've been
filming some of the episodes and it came
out quite well I'm quite happy with it
and we're GNA have uh poetry from Aran
Naga and then poetry from from roomi uh
from the he he wrote in three languages
Arabic Persian and turkey Turkish and N
can read she grew up speaking Arabic so
she's going to translate a lot of his
poetry most of his poetry has been
translated from
Persian uh Iran Iranian language and he
she can translate the ones that haven't
been translated yet so we're working on
those and khil jibran if you know him
uh and then uh SII is working on two
poets uh dharmar who's aa's
teacher and
Shanti Shan so uh so anyway we're
working on I've been working on wisdom
lately the book and uh we
are uh about 80% through the book The 27
chapters we're on the 22nd chapter uh in
the the last four years we've covered
the 22 chapters something like so we'll
be uh sorry 21 so we'll be teaching from
I'll be teaching from
wisdom uh in conjunction with medicine
Buddha and I think it will help you I
think it will help your medicine Buddha
practice really work so we'll be working
on that and then medicine Buddha
practice uh we worked really hard we
have a team that works really hard our
translation team
uh they've been together for about seven
or eight years now and uh I I designed a
translation
project when I was 22 or something 100
years
ago and uh I couldn't get funding for it
uh but about eight years ago I got
funding for it so I you know I was able
to
hire uh some translators we now have 12
translators and uh we're doing all the
great books of uh we chose one great
book from each Buddhist School in the
last 25 centuries so we're covering 25
centuries of the classics and it's going
really really well we're going to have a
class this
morning uh from one of those books uh we
used to have class
every I think three times a year and we
used to go for two two and a half weeks
and I would teach five hours a day and
it was too much uh it was too much for
me and it was too much for everybody
else we did 1200
classes uh and each class is extremely
difficult uh we
chose books from each of the great eras
of Buddhism and no one's ever tried that
since shanang the Chinese master shenan
so uh we covered all of Buddhism each
era of Buddhism has its own language
so the language that you use for the
first few hundred years is is completely
different from the language for the next
hundred years and we're doing all of
them because I'm trying to pass on all
of those languages which I learned in
the G course so uh and and afterwards so
we're working through that and this
morning we'll be doing a class with Ben
Kramer and he's translating a very
difficult text on uh you can say percept
ual Theory how do we see things how do
we perceive things and uh it's a very
beautiful class today it's a very
beautiful topic today so we'll be doing
that after this class well this class
will go till like
7:15 then we'll do Q&A for 15 minutes
and then we'll take a half hour break
here in Arizona and then we'll start the
we call it shens Sang's Tower class he
translated uh the classics of ISM in
ital in central China called
shangan and uh we're going to start
we'll switch over to his class okay uh
all right so we're uh 22 we finish 21
chapters of
wisdom and the way I'd like to start
this class is and I have
little pictures to help you remember
things okay I call them itams which is
idea image
and first one here
is yeah connecting the dots okay so I I
want
to start with wisdom I'd like to start
by the way the book is just called PR
say yeah and it just means wisdom and
then the was
extremely economical in his words he did
not waste words his poetry is very
sparse it's very skinny and he he does
not add extra words and it's every verse
of his poetry is like a Coan it's like a
mystery every single verse is like a
mystery and extremely deep and you can
read it your whole life and you and
every time you read it you find
something else in it so uh we're going
to go through his verses like that a lot
of his verses
and the structure of his book is a
mystery also each poem each verse is a
mystery there are hundreds of
verses uh but why he put the verses in
the order is also a mystery okay and I
thought maybe we could have fun here uh
trying to figure out the mystery okay
we're in the last quarter of his book we
will I don't think we'll finish this
term but we'll we'll come close and then
in the fifth term which is probably next
year we we'll finish uh his book and and
then what we do I don't know uh from
medicine Buddha our translation team
translated uh the two medicine Buddha
sutras there are only two
sutras that
survive uh from medicine Buddha and
one of them we found the
Sanskrit in a stupa in a rock stupa in
Afghanistan and uh it's uh written on
tree
bark uh it's carved on on the bark of a
tree before paper before the use of
paper and we found that copy John
Brady's project has been very important
for us for our project and we Aisha uh M
uh
scus anatol's wife has been very very
helpful to find the Sanskrit so we found
the Sanskrit there are only two medicine
Buddha sutras we translated both of them
and we published them together and that
was a lot of work that that was I don't
know thousands of hours of work and U we
finished it we published it and U it's a
beautiful book if you get it it's a it's
it is the medicine Buddha
practice uh then uh how many
years 500
plus about 2,000 years
later uh in Tibet uh medicine they say
medicine Buddha appeared again for the
first time uh to the fifth Dilma who
lived about uh I don't know four 400
years ago something like that and uh he
was a great master of Buddhism he wrote
hundreds of books hundreds of works and
uh he was interesting because he he
studied all the all the kinds of
Buddhism in Tibet he was a Saka scholar
he was a yinma scholar he was a kagi
scholar and he was a gupa scholar
obviously and he built poal
Palace uh he and his
assistant and that's a beautiful story
I'm thinking to tell you that story
sometime I'm I I just have to work on it
okay it's a beautiful Story how he did
that the part I like is the last 12
years of his life he was
dead and uh his assistant found an actor
who looked like him and that's a
interesting
story uh and uh but he he was a great
great scholar in fact Nick lashan and
Ben Kramer are cataloging his books now
it took us about two years so far and
it's a tradition that he met the
medicine Buddha and the medicine Buddha
granted him a new lineage of medicine
Buddha practice and then he was a great
writer of medicine Buddha practice and
his assistant the one who hired the
actor which I'll tell you the story
someday uh Daisy sangyo prime minister
of the country he he uh he also became a
great medical doctor and his books on
medicine ayurvedic medicine are some of
the greatest books in history uh Tibet
was in an interesting position because
to the east is uh is the ancient Chinese
uh traditional medicine TCM and then uh
to the South you have ayurva and then it
those two Traditions mixed into that so
you have a very powerful combination of
Chinese traditional medicine and and
Indian traditional medicine in Tibet and
so there was a a great he was one of the
greatest authors of medical texts and I
had an opportunity to translate for two
of the greatest the two greatest doctors
of Tibet uh for about 10 years and so
it's very uh very powerful tradition for
medicine Buddha from the fifth DM and he
wrote a new practice for the medicine
Buddha he wrote a a new uh a new way to
practice it and uh we started transl we
found it John Brady found it and we
started translating it about two years
ago and uh it's slow it takes a lot of
time takes hundreds of hours and uh we
finished a new section for you so you'll
get a new section of that uh this week
and it's finished and it's ready and I
don't know if they're translating it I
think into different languages right Tim
something like that in process uh but I
only gave it to them like a week ago so
it's usually my fault
um I think uh his medicine Buddha
s which is the instructions of how to
reach medicine bu
s uh it will be about three or 400 pages
and uh we
finished 200 the first 200 pages so uh
we'll finish the rest of it for next
year so I'm kind of split it into three
years and uh it's going to take me uh
another year to finish it so uh so but
in the meantime you get the next 100
Pages this week and you guys will be the
first people to learn it for a long time
okay and it's very beautiful uh and uh
so we're gonna be working through the
next section of medicine buddhis sna by
the fifth dilemma and by tradition it
says that he was uh that medicine Buddha
came to him and granted him this s and
so it's a new
lineage and uh it's a very complex
lineage and we traced it the tracing
took two of my San Diego vacations my
wife was quite
upset but uh we we recreated the we re
we re recreated the lineage and it was
very very difficult and we but we did it
and so uh you have the whole lineage
there and I'll be teaching you the next
100 pages okay this week so I we'll do
the second 100 pages and then uh every
time we do
some sna which means a ritual for
reaching medicine bu how do you get
medicine Buddha how do you
bribe medicine Buddha to come to your
room at diam Mountain there's a system a
bribery system and that's called sna so
we'll be going through the SNA
but does it work you
know and I got the inside
information okay like from the real
Mantra master who won the 1996 World
Series with the worst team in
history understand okay so three
lineages New York
Mets medicine Buddha and the gist wisdom
and we'll be uh mixing them together uh
so you'll get enough wisdom to see how
the medicine bu works and then you can
use it to make the medicine budle work
and then we'll actually be doing it in
practice we'll be practicing together
and we'll be experimenting with it you
know if you have a particular soccer
team that's really
bad you could try
that okay something like that all right
uh so I have a challenge for you guys
and oh by the
way because I have to teach almost every
day I have to film almost every day uh
of the year and my my my filming for the
next 15 months is already
said all the every day of filming for
the next 15 months the next 500 Days is
already booked every day is booked every
film is set up okay for the next 500
Days uh and I I like
to cross what do you call it I like to
cross
pollinate because for time reasons I
have to I I have to put some of this
class into some other class just to have
because it's 500 days straight of
filming I don't have time to you know I
don't have time to eat so uh so we're
gonna do an interesting thing uh the
peacock
parenting filming which will come out I
think in January or
February uh through
DCI um we used wisdom we used Nar they
said what poetry are you gonna use Gesa
I said I'm GNA use nar's poetry because
I have to teach it in diamond mountain
and I don't have time to get ready so I
killed two feed two deer with one
apple feed two deers with one
apple uh and I was struggling uh at the
peacock parenting class and that was
this week I was filming uh in the in the
night times this week and
uh and something strange happened to me
a couple days ago I filmed uh I had to
do three filming in one day and it was
really hard and I was tired and
uh and I did a class based on the gous
wisdom for the parenting
course and then I went home and I said
that that was a bad job I didn't do a
good job and I rare very rarely I'm not
happy with a class like once a year or
something and I just said I don't feel
comfortable with that class you know it
was based on the wisdom that we're going
to cover here it was based on the
chapters that we're going to cover this
week and uh it wasn't a brilliant class
it was a dull class and I just I went
home and I said I'm GNA throw that class
out I'm gonna film it over again uh so
we're goingon to film it over again this
week here so you get to have one
parenting
class and if you don't have kids don't
worry about it neither do
I okay
so all right and uh it'll be okay just
in case you have by accident or some uh
you know come we'll do the class
together and I was trying to use the
chapters that I'm going to cover this
week and I was trying to find the thread
of the chapters and I'm going to do it
with you right now okay so the way we're
starting the medicine Buddha practice is
we're going to go through the the names
of the six chapters that we haven't
finished yet and those are the six Dana
these are the climax of the medicine
Buddha I'm sorry these are the climax of
neous greatest book these are the climax
of the greatest book ever written by the
greatest emptiness master in history
these are supposed to be the greatest
six chapters on emptiness ever written
on this planet
and uh and I challenge you okay I'll
describe the six
chapters
and it's a
mystery why why he chose those six and
that's what I want you to think about
okay so it it doesn't the class doesn't
end in this room the class goes to your
meditation cabin and I want you to think
about it and I want you to struggle with
it and I have struggled with it and
that's why the parenting class came out
so
bad I I couldn't see uh I couldn't see
the flow you know I couldn't connect the
dots you see and I'm G to show you the
chapters of wisdom that we're going to
cover this
week
uh but I think it's hard to find a
thread and by the way Nara doesn't do
anything by accident you know he does
everything on purpose everything he ever
did had a deeper meaning okay and let's
let's work on it together okay and then
I'll ask you guys we'll have question
and answer period in about 45
minutes and uh you give me your ideas
okay here's the
question so these are supposed to be the
the climax these six
chapters are the climax of all emptiness
teachers
teachings ever given in this world okay
and and
somehow he's leading to a certain
conclusion and and that's the end of the
book chapter 27 is the end of the book
okay so these last six
chapters are
somehow it's a mystery but they are
revealing the deepest understanding of
emptiness okay and and I I'll tell you
what they're about and then I I want you
to think about it may take a couple days
or a couple years to figure out the
connection okay here's the the dots that
I want you to try to connect okay it's a
mystery I also haven't decided myself
what's the answer okay and I think in my
experience when we work together and we
talk it over together uh I think we can
come up with an answer you know so here
we go uh chapter
22 is called and by the way each of the
chapters is called an investigation
parika which means uh he wants to check
something out he he treats each one as a
mystery each chapter is like let's
investigate this okay and 22 is let's
investigate the emptiness of a
Buddha okay one one gas is tag tagata
Buddha okay let's investigate the
emptiness of Buddhas okay so that's
chapter
22 and if you learn to investigate the
emptiness of a
Buddha you can practice medicine Buddha
okay got it medicine Buddha is empty
medicine Buddha is not a
Buddha okay and somehow it
works all right so
you know it's very important for us if
we're going to figure
out how to save your soccer team how to
save your favorite soccer team which is
after all the most important use of this
stuff
uh we have to
investigate what's the emptiness of a
person who is already
perfect what's the emptiness of a person
who used medicine Buddha practice until
the make him medicine you know what's
that what's their emptiness okay got it
okay that's the first mystery and we'll
be covering it and it's a deep deep uh
topic and it's a very beautiful topic
okay if you understand the emptiness of
medicine Buddha you can do medicine
Buddha practice and if you don't
understand the emptiness of the medicine
Buddha and you try to do medicine Buddha
practice it's
Superstition okay and it won't work
Superstition doesn't work there's a joke
I don't understand your Superstition
Superstition means to stand over but I
don't understand your
Superstition uh it's a funny thing okay
chapter 23 uh it's not really an error
so much as uh
CLA okay it's an
investigation of negative states of mind
okay anger desire hatred jealousy Pride
other Specialties of myself and
everybody okay uh what's the
emptiness of
your what's the emptiness of the
negative thoughts that we have lived
with since we were children right or
longer okay what's the emptiness of
those negativities
okay that's not so hard I think right so
again from the from the last chapter to
this chapter if I say what's the
emptiness of a
Buddha and then I say what's the
emptiness of your
negativities it's pretty easy to draw
the dot draw the line between the dots
you know they must be related to each
other you get to be a Buddha by removing
your negativities something like that
okay uh so we're going to
investigate the emptiness of your
negative thoughts okay we're going to
investigate the emptiness of your anger
and your desire and your pride and your
jealousy okay it's very interesting he's
never just
investigating negativities he's
investigating the emptiness of the
negativities which is more deep and
that's deeper because that's the only
way to remove them only if you
understand the emptiness of your pride
can you remove Pride permanently from
from your mind okay nobody who doesn't
understand the emptiness of Pride could
ever be free from Pride completely it's
not possible you have to understand the
emptiness of your
negativities to remove them and if you
don't understand their emptiness you
could never remove them okay it's very
interesting okay
cool uh third
chapter let's investigate the four
higher truth
okay now in my classes lucky for you I
always make these $100
bets you know sometimes
more sometimes
less uh but I I like
to I don't know just students try they
stay awake better if I if I make $100
better every once in a while people are
like right now for
[Music]
example I can't even see word Smith but
I can see his
[Applause]
face you know so here we go here's a
$100 bet nobody can tell me the hey I
want to
know we're going to talk about the
higher truths I want to know number one
what they are
and number
two why is it true that you can I'd call
them the
four noble TR Noble
Truth
go KY K's two
truth wait I'll say the question it's
suspicious when they raise their hand
and they don't know the
question
uh for Tru I want to know why noble is a
bad translation
and I want to know what they
are if you want to be fancy you could
explain the order but you don't have
to good and why would Noble be a bad
translation why they're called for Noble
Truth in most
books which is a bad translation of the
word a it doesn't describe U the State
of Mind of the person who has traveled
the path who saw emptiness who saw
emptiness yeah that's all the word is
Arya CH Arya s for ARA truth and uh so
for I don't know a hundred years in
English people have mistranslated it as
Noble which Aya can mean rarely Noble or
higher but we call it higher truth okay
but they're called Aya because they are
seen directly by a person who just saw
EMP this okay all right so 100 bucks for
you now where do you
collect Ellie do he collect from you rob
Rob's gonna hand out the money I hope we
have
enough just after we give the money we
have all these
fundraisers that's that's how cinam and
me
weren okay uh no
pressure okay uh that's chapter 24 so so
far we got the emptiness of a
budha then the emptiness of
negativities and then the emptiness of
the four truth okay and in
general
it was the first teaching ever given by
Lord budha and by the way he went to it
three times 12 12 repetitions right and
then um most of his audience saw
emptiness directly at that
time and
uh that's
a so how does that tie together we're
gonna check out the emptiness of a
Buddha medicine Buddha and then we're
going to check out the emptiness of
their negativities which they don't have
anymore and then we're going to check
out the
emptiness of this logic it's the
ultimate logic we are suffering we are
dying there's a reason why we're dying
you can stop it you just have to find
the path to stop it those those are the
four higher truths is he
emphasizing a person who just saw
emptiness and then saw the for truth you
see is he emphasizing that or is he
emphasizing the first teaching that
Buddha ever gave I I don't know okay
that's up to you uh and and you don't
have to decide in this class I'll take
some
opinions uh when we get to the Q&A but
uh I think it's a very
useful it's a it's a good use of your
meditation time in your retreat okay to
to sit quietly at diamond mountain and
think about these questions is the
purpose of being here at diamond
mountain and uh it's a beautiful
beautiful retreat center it's my
Ukrainian
France that we invited from Kiev to come
live in the greatest city in the world
which is called
Rimrock
uh you know I when they came here they
were like wow this is something this
place is something you know and it's a
great uh place to meditate and it's a
great place to have a breakthrough in
your own heart you know you've got
you've got I don't know nine 10
days uh of Silence you know you have a
choice to put down your cell phone for
nine or 10 days do you have the courage
to do
it you know or is your habit too strong
are you addicted too to your cell phone
you you have an
opportunity this week to put down your
cell phone and we don't force you we
used to turn off we built the retreat
center in a place that didn't have
internet and it was hard to find a place
like that and we paid a lot of
money I call this The Blood Sweat and
Tears Retreat Center we had a lot of
trouble here we had a lot of suffering
we had a lot of work it was a lot of
money and you know now it's this
beautiful retreat center and if you come
from a far away place in an airplane and
come to Diamond Mount retreat center and
sit down in your cabin and check your
internet it's kind of super silly okay I
mean silly I'm being polite
okay uh bad idea okay said it's a you
know we
don't I'm not gonna Peak through your
window although I will walk
around and I hope you guys can put down
your phones for a week and just
experience what it feels like and uh
think about these
questions and and you it can change your
life we had a business class we're doing
an MBA course I filmed that last week uh
we were filming uh MBA courses
and and we were talking about Innovation
we were talking about
some uh manufacturing
processes uh Innovation and
Manufacturing Pro processes and we were
talking about some of the ones we did in
Manhattan that weren't Buffett bought
and the process
and uh those came out of
retreat a lot of those Pro a lot of
those Factory processes that we sold to
Warren Buffett came out of retreat a
deep Retreat so uh you know you have a
choice you can just stare at some
YouTube video of guy hitting home
run which is what I did last night uh or
you can turn on you know just put your
phone down and and go into this deep
questions of medicine Buddha and and
emptiness okay and I really really
encourage you uh to spend the week that
way okay I I'm not gonna babysit you and
it's up to you you want to ruin your
week it's up to you but uh I'll tell you
something you know we sold that company
for a quarter billion dollars it became
the largest one in the world for Diamond
jewelry and
those ideas came from Deep Retreats and
I think you might want to try it you
know uh it's kind of cool it's kind of
really exciting and obviously I didn't
spend all the time just doing that but I
spent some time doing that and and and
it was useful okay all right chapter 25
an investigation of
Nirvana okay so is is he just add
who Aran n by the way we never call him
Naga we call him Aran okay he's the
number one Arya in
history his book is the number one
emptiness book in history in two and a
half thousand years and uh and we just
finished a beautiful book by him called
the
60 verses on how to prove
emptiness and uh it's 67 70 pages every
single page takes I don't know 10 20 30
hours and we finished it took seven
years Nick lha finished his book and
it's amazing and it's almost 700 pages
on on how to prove emptiness uh
so what's the connection you know what
what's what's the connection between
that and the three chapters we just
mentioned okay why is he just
add you know and by the way some people
when they read a a when they see a
structure like this for example in a
famous yoga book there's some questions
about the structure for zero
dollar which book come on there's only
two yoga
Sutra okay the yoga Sutra that the order
of the chapters is strange especially
the fourth chapter you know why it comes
there why it's so different from the
other three chapters a lot of Scholars
have said it's it's somebody later a
hundred years later somebody glued
something onto the book you know uh and
and so a lot of people when they get to
A Book Like
wisdom they will say oh somebody glued
on some chapters and that's why it gets
chaotic at the end and it's not true
it's all by neard you can smell n when
you read
n when you when you work with ar n a lot
you get to where you can recognize his
word we found 141 books by Nar in John
Brady's database only 10 are known of
okay uh we found 141 and we threw out a
couple We There were some that we didn't
accept into the database we think it's
not him doesn't sound like him okay
there's a few
books by someone who has a name that
called Krishna nagaj like black nagaj
there's another one called Pure nag and
like that and those we decided to keep
because they're obviously n they are
obviously by written by an emptiness
Master
Okay Okay um
next chapter
26 uh an investigation of the 12 lengths
of the Wheel of
Life which is Sugi
uh expertise his book was just finished
his first book on the Wheel of Life was
just finished and uh it's a very deep
presentation of The Wheel of Life from
500 years
ago and then he wanted to suffer
more and uh John Brady's project found
an extremely rare presentation of The
Wheel of Life 2,000 years ago by
vasu and We're translating it and it's
extremely
deep and so su's working on
that it's an interesting book because
basab Bandu wrote the book for the
lowest Buddhist
school at has a
confession uh for criticizing his
brother
aunga and uh then
a said that well and then he apologized
to his brother and he asked his brother
should he cut his tongue out he offered
to cut his tongue out because he had
criticized his brother his brother said
H yeah I you keep your tongue for you
know
and but you could write a book about
about the school that you're coming from
and that the school you're about to
dump you could write a book about them
because once you join up with me no
one's going to want to study that school
anymore so he wrote the Abid darosa
which is the the great great
presentation of the first school and
it's a great book uh and then he came
out of the closet and then he felt free
to to show his is that he was really in
mind only school and he did that in sug
gang's new
book so it's extremely interesting and
extremely beautiful and uh we were
working on it last week I
think okay so that's basically I think
he put that chapter in there for to
gang uh but why does he go in this order
why does he talk about Buddhas and then
he talks about anger and then he talks
about his first teaching and then he
jumps to Nirvana and then he gets into
the Wheel of Life why why that order it
doesn't seem very logical okay somewhere
there's a twisted arus logic
there okay and I I ask you to unravel it
okay it's a mystery it's a mystery to me
it destroyed my parenting course I got
no I I that's why I have to refilm that
class cuz I'm like what you know okay uh
last
one let's
investigate viewpoints and Ben Kramer
just finished his first book all these
books are coming out we had a wonderful
sponsor uh they basically fed the mix
nuts for seven years it caused a weird
phenomenon in their house and as a
result we have lots of babies coming
out and uh all I know we had four kids I
think came out uh something like that uh
so we've been uh looking
into uh Ben Kramer translated a book
called
SED and this was a Hot
Topic about 500 years ago in in the
middle of China okay strange I mean it's
influenced by the
Mongols and uh by by by others East
Tibetans uh Central
Chinese uh inner
Mongolians and what's that language
standing inner
Mongolia mchu and weager so it's a very
strange time in history
and sitting there in the middle of
China exposed to
Confucianism DSM Buddhism
Islam nestorian
Christianity you know all these strange
religions are sitting there in that area
at the same
time uh Mongolian Shaman beliefs they're
all cooking in that same area at the
same time and they got interested in
comparative religion so they got into
the study of different people people's
viewpoints and they started writing
books about comparative religion and
they're amazing they're incredible so uh
Ben Kramer translated one of them and it
presents
religions it's a book of 101
religions okay and it's
amazing uh to
compare 101 different
religions uh over this his over the
history of about 30
centuries uh sitting in a Melting Pot of
the greatest philosophies of Asia uh
confusion ISM dosm Buddhism
Shamanism even even Christianity and
Islam in all sitting there he translated
it and it's an amazing book it's an
amazing uh you you should read it it's
it's amazing why am I talking about that
the last chapter of
thear is an investigation of religions
or or different ideas you
know what is it about people that they
create 101 different religions you know
by the way some of those religions died
a thousand years ago we we don't know
much about them we know their
philosophy but why do some religions in
the time of Jesus there were
100 over a 100 religions current in
Palestine and one survive or two survive
and what is it what what is it why do
they survive okay so that's the last
chapter of
nagaj you know here's all the different
viewpoints that human beings come up
with and what's the emptiness of those
viewpoints okay what's the emptiness of
all the religions that are human beings
have ever thought of it's a great
question it's very interesting what's
the emptiness of a human being's hunger
to create a
religion okay it's very interesting okay
and that's his last chapter and then
he's like I'm
done okay now how do those how do those
six chapters
flow into each other if you crack the
the
mystery i' I'd say you're ready to
practice medicine Buddha okay that's
that's what we're doing here we are
practicing medicine
Buddha by
examining spiritual
wisdom from the gar okay because if you
just repeat medicine Buddha prayers and
medicine Buddha mantras and you don't
think about it that will never work for
you it's not possible and then it's
truly Superstition it's just
superstition okay and I it really
bothers me I don't know why I want to
yell at people who do that you know it's
really irritating to me I don't know why
it's just it's like you're so close to
the real truth and you don't even think
about it you just want to Bubba Bubba
you know just really irritating
okay all right uh I'd like to review
what we covered in the fifth D St so far
we have 15 minutes and then we will do
Q&A for 15 minutes then we'll take a
nice I call it a semi breakfast break I
like semi I have a
cafe some of you have been there we have
a first step breakfast Second Step
breakfast third step breakfast you can
have breakfast there for about six
hours that's my idea of a good time so
uh we're g to have uh I talked somebody
meeing my wife into uh sponsoring coffee
a green
drink and a and orange fresh orange
juice for all you guys so uh we'll we'll
take a break at
[Music]
730 1 sorry and then right no yeah
you're right okay no no we'll Q&A at
7:15 we'll stop class at 7:30 you get
your uh first course of
breakfast uh which is either coffee
orange juice or green drink or all three
and uh we'll do that every day like that
okay okay uh next item you guys
Francisco it's the step yeah we have
finished four steps
of the medicine budha practice okay we
have already finished four different
steps of the medicine Buddha sadna sadna
means uh a practice that you can take to
your retreat center and reach the
medicine Buddha while you're there s
means uh a practice that helps you reach
a Buddha okay so we are learning the
medicine Buddha s and an an
means it it's a method and sad means to
reach s means method for reaching medic
okay Sid for example comes from the
same like
Sid which means the one who has reached
the goal okay all right uh so we we
finished four steps of the medicine
Buddha s okay by the fifth dama okay and
supposedly it was granted to him by by
medicine all right here we go
uh next
picture uh I call this where we've gone
already so you see the back of the car
okay like we've already covered some
parts of the sna I'm going to repeat the
parts that we
covered uh the sna reading that you all
get for this week we'll have all the old
Parts in it also okay so here here's the
old parts that you're going to see in
there if you didn't come last year for
example we'll catch you up and and we'll
we're going to re review the parts that
we covered last year so here's here's
the parts we covered last
year
uh you can skip the next one which just
says what we covered already uh number
one the the sna in general next picture
of
Francisco uh next one yeah yeah
um the first part of the sodna covers
General Buddhism okay General Buddhist
practice all right so the the first part
of your practice here this week is
practices that you would cover in any
Buddhist practice okay General Buddhist
practice and here's a list of them for
you okay uh next
yeah these are the parts that we
finished for $100 what's hiding in that
list I think it was Stanley right
hgy seven
Loops which means what like a tree it's
a it's a a pre pre preliminary
meditation practice yeah this is good
yeah seven
[Music]
preliminaries uh for all meditation
practice okay seven steps you should be
taking every day this
week to start your practice and so the
fif L starts mainly with those seven
preliminaries but calling them
preliminary is a little
misleading and I'm not offering you
$100 because this is going to get expens
[Music]
why is it misleading to call them seven
preliminary yeah I should take the $100
back we usually do the dedication after
the practice that's okay now
listen sometimes people give a $100
answer to a Zer
question yeah always irritated me that
people say on seven preliminaries I say
but one of them's not a preliminary you
do it
afterwards okay got it number seven is
dedicating The Good Karma of your
meditation sessions hopefully it's after
the meditation session or else there is
no meditation okay all right so here's
uh here's where he goes in his son we
finished this already it's just a review
for you guys you got the whole
sna 200 pages of the S there's 300 just
total I'll give you the rest next year I
promise uh opening prostration okay and
normally normally uh someone who writes
a Buddhist book will bow down to all the
teacherss of their lineage okay and it's
good luck to honor all the teachers who
came before because when you write a new
book you get lots of obstacles and so to
to overcome those obstacles normally at
the beginning of a Buddhist book we will
bow down to the teachers of the class to
collect special Good Karma to prevent
obstacles okay all right then he honors
the
lineage and I will say more about that
later okay his lineage
is unusual very unusual for the medicine
bu because he was so eclectic and no one
has been that eclectic
uh there's only two D llamas who have
been that eclectic who have been really
embraced uh all the different religions
and was open to all the different
religions current D is is the second to
be so open to
everybody uh honoring the lineage
committing to the practice of renewal
that's called what is renewal and
purification
into so yeah so and so means
to uh fix or you can say renew and then
Jong means to purify and normally you do
the Jung before the so it should have be
it should have been called Jung
so okay but soong you may have heard the
Tibetan word so uh basically this whole
list is Sak Jang
$100
[Music]
sck
I'm collecting goodness and purifying
bad Deeds good 100 bucks back there okay
uh
yeah basically the whole uh warm up to
your daily meditation you shouldn't go
into a
meditation without Sak J which is so J
okay Jang means
first make some acknowledge M of your
mistakes for the past couple days okay
and we all have them okay we all have
them all right and just be honest with
yourself okay I got irritated and
venerable C and Tim and you know
Angelo like that okay like just
admit at least admit to
yourself uh little boo boos you mean in
the last or big ones in the last few
days okay and then uh admit them and
then equal weight to $100 equal weight
to who said it
Jen Y say or Jenny did you
say $50
each Okay g Jenny yeah yeah we always
say equal equal attention to the good
things you've done this week okay and
and I'll tell you something we learned
in
DCI with the coffee meditation
instructions people have a strange
inability to admit how nice they are
okay it seems like really good people
have trouble admitting that they're good
people okay it just seems to be human
nature okay so uh
equal equal
time before your meditation to
appreciating yourself okay and if you
don't do that you're then you can then
you
can fail then you're failed Buddhist
okay if you don't appreciate what a good
Buddhist you are you're a failed
Buddhist how's
that okay if you're a Buddhist and you
don't
appreciate the good things you do you
you messed up okay and you can add that
to your confession
tomorrow
okay all right but
please uh you are
required uh during this part of the sna
which is the warm up for the sun you are
required to think of the good things
you're doing and if you don't do it the
sna doesn't
work okay if you don't do it the doesn't
work okay you can't leave out half of
the preliminaries and expect the rest of
sna to work it doesn't work like that
you have to give equal time to
appreciating all the good stuff you're
doing and everyone in this room is doing
really sweet beautiful things you just
have to admit it to yourself okay and
you are required to do that okay so you
can beat yourself up up you have every
right and responsibility to beat
yourself up uh then equal
time okay did I say equal yes equal time
on thinking about the good things you've
done and if you're like me I don't know
what it is when I get to the equal time
on things I did well like before I go to
bed I start thinking about mistakes I
made it's weird you know they just push
their way into the room and I'm like oh
you guys come later this is the time for
the good people you know this is the
time to appreciate myself and they're
like yeah but you were so selfish and
I'm like I know I'm selfish I already
confessed that you know we're trying to
find something good I did yesterday you
know so don't let them boss you around
okay like just say come back tomorrow
during confession time we're done with
confession time this is rejoicing time
time you know and you you definitely did
great stuff today and it's not
Pride to to appreciate the good stuff
you're doing it's wisdom it's a kind of
wisdom okay it's it's good
reinforcement of of your goodness okay
and you have to spend that time you must
spend equal time okay I'm looking at sha
ping I know I know you don't do
it it's like oh I didn't spend enough
time on the NBA program and I'm like you
didn't spend enough time now shut up try
to appreciate yourself okay all
right we got a few minutes let's finish
this list uh bow down bow
down after many years of bowing down in
preliminaries I realized you're just
supposed to
appreciate somebody who's a good person
that's all you don't have to get up and
bow down it hurts your knees and it's
okay okay
mentally appreciating a good person in
your life I was with Rob Russ Ander
yesterday me and S spent four hours
doing finances with him
and he's a
beautiful
honest inspiring person you know and
when I bow down you know I just think of
him he's one of the people I think of
and uh and that's it that's all okay
you're not bowing down to some bu you
never met or something
okay that time that part of your
preliminary is supposed to be spent
appreciating someone good in your life
okay and there must be somebody okay all
right uh making offerings I always make
offerings to that
person uh russer likes coffee he likes
three
cups give him one two three okay in my
in my visualization I offer him three
cups of cof and then uh confession I do
my
confession then take joy in the Good
Deeds you did okay please don't short it
please give it equal time uh then ask
your teacher to teach in in your mind
okay ask people to teach you and the
biggest lesson in life are the ones you
get from the in your life okay
so don't go looking for these holy
people okay the people who irritate you
are your greatest teachers all right if
someone can irritate you you're not
there
yet okay so the ones who irritate you
have a special
value that's why they have such an
endless
suppliers all right
uh then ask your teacher to stay ask ask
those irritating people to stay in your
life and they will anyway
uh and then after
your after your meditation dedicate the
Good Karma okay and that's a very
beautiful uh spreading of beauty there's
an opposite
practice uh in in Buddhism called the
what's it called mupa yeah
it's called a uh disaster
meditation and you
uh starting with a a hole in your skull
you imagine that the whole world is
rotting okay it's called a it's called
ugliness meditation and you you you put
a
little like what do you call open sore
here and then it gets worse and worse
and and it spreads and it spreads to
your body and then it spreads to your
state and then it spreads to Coast to
Coast you're supposed to reach the west
coast and the east coast and the whole
United States is like a nuclear bomb has
just destroyed everything all skeletons
Rotting Flesh then you bring it all
back to here and that's called a that's
an old time of Abid
Dharma sadness meditation okay this is
the opposite you're supposed to start
here with beauty like a flower and then
flowers flowers flowers flowers flowers
all the way to the West Coast and the
east coast and then the whole country is
covering with flow okay and that's
that's the last one here all right we're
gonna do Q&A uh I have a rule for Q&A
three parts number one a question about
the stuff we covered today which would
be really refreshing but no one ever
asks
uh number
two uh a personal question you have you
know about your personal life and guess
what everybody online everybody here has
exactly the same problems as you and we
appreciate it when you ask the question
and we don't have to like I have this
girlfriend problem or something like
that you know and we all have it but we
don't want to mention it
so uh personal question number three uh
some people have some kind of burning
philosophy question ever since gessi
Michael said something about emptiness
it's been bothering them and here's your
big chance to ask it okay
so go for it I'll let Tim Tim can you
choose people okay
hi gisha yeah by the way any question is
fine I I don't care the whole point of
the gashi program is to
answer uh difficult immediate questions
okay and anything you want to ask
this I have a question and I know that
it bothers many people hold the Box
CL I know this question bothers many
people
uh you probably know that there is a war
in my country in
Ukraine and um kind of we were
practicing uh we were doing something
this almost two years but it doesn't
look like it is getting better you know
like even more there is another conflict
uh in Middle East and um I mean I have a
personal question what I do run you know
like I I really do I think I do my best
but probably something is missing and I
know many people they practicing
medicine Buddha uh they were given by
vulnerable jigman and another practice
that I don't have but I know they are
practicing maxor something like that so
is there anything that we should
understand about it
to like what is the you know like what
we should do about it
yeah okay good question
um every time you somebody asks a
question like that I think of the same
thing
uh I I had I was involved in an abortion
in um when I was in college and uh I at
at the time all my college professors
and my parents and they were like it's
okay it's okay you know then I met my
teacher and he said oh that's that's bad
you know and I'm like well how do I
clean that and he he gave me basically
he told me to teach a kids
class
uh and and I was living in a Mongolian
uh community in near New York so there
were a couple thousand Mongolian
refugees from World War
II and the US government brought them
over after World War II and there were a
couple thousand
uh people and they had survived the
concentration camps these are people who
were tough enough to jump over the fence
and get away and men and women and uh
they
were all traumatized they were all of
them badly traumatized and so you can't
talking a couple thousand people and me
and my teacher were living
there and it was really hard
they were very traumatized and a lot of
them were on heroin or alcohol or you
know still doing this you know you know
because they some of them were captured
by the Germans to uh dig the T
trenches and a lot of them were killed
in the concentration camps and so they
were they were very very
seriously messed up and they were also
very
against
uh anyone who wasn't Mongolian you know
which means me and uh I was the only
American living there and uh then
there's one Tibetan which is my teacher
and they were
very difficult to live with them really
difficult and they were very suspicious
of us and for 20 years 25 years and it
was hard it was really hard and there
was one one man uh who had an open
mind uh and he was The Treasure of the
temple and he was this very I don't have
picture you have this picture here I'll
show you his
picture you should thank him his name is
hanor soov and
uh he reached out to me and he reached
out to my teacher and he said I'll take
care of you don't worry you know you
will survive live here I'll I'll I'll do
it I'll take care of it you know and
we're like thanks cuz it was really
really hard to be there and everyone was
suspicious of us and everyone was kind
of against us and uh
he we made a that's his
picture he passed away
recently so we're gonna have a special
uh ceremony for
him uh and his family's going to come
from New Jersey this picture was taken
50 years ago but he passed away a few
days ago a few weeks ago and uh so we're
going to dedicate the fire offering to
him I would not be here if he wasn't if
he didn't protect me in this very
difficult Community uh I wouldn't be
here I wouldn't be teaching and only
because of him so his family will come
and
uh and the kids uh my teacher the reason
I met his family was uh I taught the
kids for 15 years I had a kids class for
the Mongolian kids and his kids came
three kids they're gonna come this week
they're old now they're like 50s 55 okay
I Tau them when they when they were this
High you know and
uh and that was my teacher's
uh assignment for me to to clean the
karma of the
abortion you know and and uh okay
Grandpa's stories usually come back to
the
point and at my ages sometimes I forget
what the point was but uh the point I do
remember I asked my teacher uh how long
do I have to teach his you know these
kids how how long do I have to teach the
kids
program and he he looked at me and he
said until the karma is finished you
have to keep doing it and I'm like well
like a week like six weeks you know he
said until it's finished and I'm like
how am I going to know when it's
finished he says you'll know you will
know and you have to keep going until
it's finished and he and I I know I
insisted give me a date give me a time
give me when's the war going to end
what's the date of the last person to
die and he's like that's up to you he
refuse to answer me he said that's up to
you you know it's how how well do you do
your
purification how well do you teach your
his kids you know and it it took 15
years
okay and I I did it for 15
years and it finished okay then it
finish
so just have to keep going till it
finishes and don't think you're wasting
your time and don't think it's not
working or something like that some
Kars some karmas are very
serious and they need a lot of work so
he used to say uh your karma is like
cement and we don't know how hard it
got so it could be still soft it could
be quite hard you know we don't know and
so his answer his famous answer was you
keep going until it's done and and you
actually don't have a
choice so that's my answer and but I I
believe
uh I'll tell you one last thing I went
to
Vietnam uh
I when I was in college uh I went to
jail uh working against the Vietnam War
I went to jail and
uh and uh our army was beat by the
Vietnamese Army just just because they
were so brave they didn't have 1% of the
American money or the bombs or the
weapons they didn't have
1% but they beat the Americans you know
and uh the main leader was hoi Min and
um I
uh the first time I went to Vietnam uh
to teach I was uh I I get i t I talked
in Hanoi
which is the capital of of North Vietnam
and um I got up on the stage and they
put a statue of hoi men next to me and
I'm
like you know and uh we taught at uh I
don't know if you guys remember you were
there I don't but we taught at a place
where uh the North Vietnamese Army had
had dug tunnels underground to to to
escape the
bombing and uh we taught there we had a
retreat many of the participants were
ampute they had lost legs they had lost
arms in the
bombing and we did yoga together and I'm
sitting there trying to help this guy do
yoga he doesn't have a leg and they were
so kind to me and they were so beautiful
and
so you know no hatred nothing just love
you know and I was like I'm supposed to
teach you you're teaching me you know we
we did so many terrible things there and
here they are you know I was you know I
almost went there I almost was sent
there you know and here they are being
so kind and U so as an old man I'll tell
you something time changes all things
and there will come a day when we're all
sitting having a class in Moscow or
something there will come a day when
we're all enjoying each other in in
Russia or or in Ukraine and and
everyone's just loving each other there
will come a day just be
patient and I've seen it as an old man I
tell you I've seen it you know so
okay one more question
Timothy
seconds why you talk so much
Grandpa well that's a long
question I think we'll just
stop uh so
8:00 we will have uh a mix nuts class
what I did with the mix nuts classes
rather
than by the way we've had 1200 classes
1260 classes rather than have a bunch of
classes at the same time
time we decided to have uh three classes
a week so we'll be having and the theory
is no matter where I am in the world we
do the class and so we're going to do
the mixnuts class this morning uh for
Ben Kramer's book and then Monday
evening uh I think it's uh 4 to 7 we'll
do two more classes and we'll just keep
doing that every Saturday and every
Monday for the rest of your life okay so
uh so Satur Saturday morning is mainly
for Europe and America and then uh
Monday night is mainly for Asia for
Tuesday Morning in Asia so we'll just
keep doing that uh forever okay so
because of that rule we're going to have
a we're going to have a translation
class in half an hour and we'll take a
break anything else Timothy I should be
announcing see you guys at 8:00 have a
nice break and we'll see you at 8